מזל טוב Mazal tov שנה טובה shana tova again, good see we
are today's דף daf is י"ד, yud-daled, we pick up at the
top of י"ד yud-daled and the issue was that the משנה mishna
is talking about returning documents of debt and we're in a section
of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia where we're going to spend in the
next few days, not really dealing with מציאה, metzia, but really dealing
with these issues about debt documents. And the debate in the משנה
mishna was do you return a debt document if you don't return
it if there are liens and then according to another opinion you
never return it but we're presuming that's because the other opinion holds
that there's always presumed to be liens and there were two explanations
in the גמרא, gemara, one is that we're talking that you don't
return it if even if the person excuse me you don't return
it if the person says that there is that he didn't the
לוה loveh says he did not borrow money, which makes an enormous
amount of sense, but then the question is what's the logic of
the one who says you do return it, and it forced us
to say that the one who says you do return it when
there's no liens is basically saying that the document is worthless. The
better explanation was was that the case was that the לוה loveh
does agree that it belongs to the מלוה, malveh, and nevertheless you
don't return it because even though the לוה loveh is agreeing, the
liens means that there are purchasers לקוחות lekuchot that can be injured
in the process. And that's why you don't return it. And the
one and then the only question is if it's not explicit in
the document there's still presumed to be liens. Okay, that was the
approach that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan took and that was the ברייתות
braitot that we had supporting that approach and as we said, even
though you normally aren't concerned about that in a normal case of
a loan, why don't you assume that something, you know, fishy is
up, nevertheless here the fact that the document has fallen on the
ground raises suspicions, either why would a person be sloppy with it
or the idea we've been talking about, if it's on the ground
it stops sort of being testimony so the restore to the מלוה
malveh turns it into testimony so any possible concern is present and
the concern here is is that maybe it was actually already paid
up and we're returning it to the מלוה malveh and the מלוה
malveh is going to use it to take money to take property
illegitimately from the purchasers and he's got some deal going on together
with the לוה. loveh. So again, something we would normally never be
concerned about, but when there are liens and it's on the floor
and and we have to restore it to the מלוה, malveh, that
is the concern. Yes, Michael? Well, this interpretation according to the opinion
that says it's worthless and you return to the מלוה, malveh, but
then okay, let's say the loan was, you know, three years from
now, right, he's got to pay it back, so it gets lost
in year one, so the מלוה malveh has it, two years from
now he says, Oh, here's my document. No, no, the reason it
was worthless is not because it was on the floor, the reason
it was worthless was because it didn't have אחריות achrayut written in
it. No, no, I understand that, but then what's to prevent him
from actually saying this is a real document two years from now
when the loan becomes due? It's not a real document, it doesn't
have the אחריות achrayut written in it, it's a worthless document. Oh,
so it can never be collected? Correct, correct. So what was the
point of
having a משנה mishna to begin with this stuff? I don't know,
so now the I don't know, but that's the point of the
גמרא. gemara. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this: okay,
and תיובתא tiyuvta to pick up three lines from the top because
we had a ברייתא braita that explicitly supported this read, that it
was a case of חייב מודה, chayiv modeh, which is רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan approach, and and contradicted all the other reads. So the
גמרא gemara now says that תיובתא דשמואל בתרתי, tiyuvta de-Shmuel be-tartei, so
that ברייתא braita that we quoted yesterday also contradicts שמואל Shmuel in
two ways. חדא כרבי אליעזר, chada ke-Rabbi Eliezer, י"ד עמוד א', yud-daled
amud-alef, חדא כרבי אליעזר, chada ke-Rabbi Eliezer, one is the same way
it sort of contradicted רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer דהא מוקי מתניתין בשאין
חייב מודה de-ha mukei matnitin beshe-ein chayiv modeh because he שמואל Shmuel
like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the משנה mishna about not returning
the document is only when the לוה loveh denies that he borrowed
the money, but the ברייתא braita makes it very clear that the
לוה loveh agrees he borrowed the money and nevertheless you don't return
it because of the injury to the לקוחות. lekuchot. וחדא, ve-chada, the
other way it contradicts שמואל Shmuel is and we're going to see
this in a few days, דאמר שמואל מצא שטר הקנאה בשוק יחזיר
לבעלים. de-amar Shmuel matza shtar hakna'ah bashuk yachazir le-ba'alim. If you find
a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah in the marketplace בשוק, bashuk, again a
שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah is a שטר shtar that even before it
was given over, the קנין kinyan was done and the transfer took
place, so the indebtedness of the document took place even before the
money was lent and the שטר shtar was handed over. So in
that case, you return it to the owners, and now שמואל's Shmuel
going to say this even if the לוה loveh says it's a
forgery or if the לוה loveh says it's been paid up, שמואל
Shmuel always says you return it to the לוה loveh no to
the lender, why? Because he says we're never concerned of פירעון pira'on
that it's been paid off and of קנוניא kenunyan of some type
of scheme. Okay, so the חידוש chiddush later is we've already seen
that idea now mentioned now, but שמואל Shmuel goes so far to
say that you're not concerned about פירעון pira'on even if the לוה
loveh is saying that he paid it off, you're not concerned about
פירעון pira'on because if that were true the document would be torn
up and you always give it back to the מלוה. malveh. And
in this ברייתא, braita, תיובתא, tiyuvta, it's a contradiction to him, דקתני
de-katanei because שמואל Shmuel says מצא שטר הקנאה בשוק יחזיר לבעלים ולא
חיישינן לפירעון matza shtar hakna'ah bashuk yachazir le-ba'alim ve-lo chashinan le-pira'on and
we're never concerned about פירעון, pira'on, not just לא חיישינן לפירעון ולקנוניא,
lo chashinan le-pira'on ve-la-kenunyan, right, even if it's not a scheme, the
לוה's loveh saying don't give it back, don't give it back, I
paid it up, according to שמואל Shmuel we don't listen to him,
we're never concerned, if he had paid it up it'd be torn
up and you always give it back. And in this ברייתא, braita,
תיובתא, tiyuvta, it's a contradiction to him. דתני הכא אף על פי
ששניהם מודים לא יחזיר, d'tani hacha af al pi she'shneihem modim lo
yachzir, even if the לוה loveh agrees and they both agree, if
there are liens in it don't give it back, לא לזה ולא
לזה, lo l'zeh v'lo l'zeh, why? או דחיישינן לפרעון, o d'chashinan l'piraon,
the only reason you wouldn't give it back is you're afraid that
it's been paid up, so you see even if it's not torn
up, we are saying it's possible the document has been paid up,
and certainly would that be true if the לוה loveh said that
it hadn't been paid up, ודחיישינן לפרעון, v'd'chashinan l'piraon, that you would
be concerned and you would not give it back. So all of
that is just wrapping up yesterday. Now the גמרא Gemara sort of
moves on to another point. Related, but another point. אמר שמואל מאי
טעמא דרבנן, Amar Shmuel mai ta'ama d'Rabanan, what's the reason of the
רבנן Rabanan that say that don't give it back even if there
is no liens written in the documents? We've just gone through a
whole point saying that the reason you don't give it back, the
לוה loveh agrees but you don't give it back because you have
to protect the לקוחות, lakochos, that they might be injured by this
because maybe the שטר shtar was already paid up. Okay, that makes
sense for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says don't give it back
when there are liens, but the רבנן Rabanan say don't give it
back even if there are no liens. What's the logic for that?
If there are no liens, it's only the לוה loveh being hurt,
and he says that he paid it. So מאי טעמא דרבנן, mai
ta'ama d'Rabanan, what's the reason for the רבנן? Rabanan? קסברי אחריות טעות
סופר הוא, kasvari achrayut taut sofer hu, they are of the opinion
the absence of writing liens in the document is considered to be
an oversight of the סופר, sofer, and therefore it is not a,
and you know, it is an error of the סופר, sofer, meaning
every document is presumed to have liens in it. Now you know
there's two ways of sort of saying that. There's basically saying like
it sincerely means that, that ninety-eight percent of all the things would
have liens written in, and if it ever accidentally gets left out
we always like by context assume it's there because we genuinely assume
it was a slip and he had meant to write it and
accidentally he didn't. Okay. But the other way of sort of saying
it is that like forget about whether it's a mistake of the
סופר sofer or not, we're just sort of defining, by definition, you
know, that every loan comes with liens. If you want, right exactly,
if you want your loan to not have liens, okay, but as
we know, you know, if you're the מלוה, malveh, even if things
are assumed and are taken for granted, you want to say them
explicitly, you know, you want to just, there should never be any
question. But the basic rule is that we're just assuming that every
loan that comes with a document has liens associated with it, and
if you agree not to have liens, you have to explicitly exclude
them. You have to opt out rather than opt in. You know,
that's the other way of saying אחריות טעות סופר הוא achrayut taut
sofer hu means if you don't want liens, you have to opt
out. Otherwise you're assumed to have liens. Okay, but one way or
the other, that's what the רבנן Rabanan hold, and therefore, because there
are always liens in the document, you never return it because we're
always trying to protect the לקוחות. lakochos. It's essentially what you're bothering
to write down the שטר shtar for, you know, even if you
have עדים. edim. What? That's why you're bothering to write a שטר.
shtar. Although again, there's other reasons too, because if מלוה חברו בעדים
malveh chaveiro b'edim maybe אין צריך לפורעו בעדים, ein tzarich l'poro b'edim,
I mean, written proof is always better. Pass it down to your
kids. But anyway, but nevertheless, right, we are always assuming that liens
are present. So אמר ליה רבה בר אידי לרב אידי בר אבין,
amar lei Rabba bar Iddi l'Rav Iddi bar Avin, ומי אמר שמואל
הכי, u'mi amar Shmuel hachi, did שמואל Shmuel really say this, that
there's always liens assumed to be present in the document? והאמר שמואל,
v'ha'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says, שבח שפר ושיעבוד צריך לימלך. shevach shefer
v'shibud tzarich limalech. So this is a nice little way to remember.
It's a nice little mnemonic. It's got three things in it. They
all start with a ש, shin, and it's like, you know, שבח
שפר shevach shefer is like one syllable, שיעבוד shibud is two. Anyway,
it's a nice שבח שפר. shevach shefer. Anyway, I'll test you tomorrow
if you remember the phrase, שבח שפר ושיעבוד. shevach shefer v'shibud. Okay,
so there are these three things the סופר sofer has to ask.
Now what does that mean? I'm selling here Michael a plot of
land. We're going to get, this is going to be a dominant
case for today. It's not a loan, but the point is some
creditor might come and seize that land from Michael. And then Michael
is going to want to get reimbursed from me for the loss,
right? Because he gave me ten thousand dollars for the land. Some
creditor of mine takes it. He's going to want his money back.
All right. So if he wants his money back, we have to
do three things. I, the סופר sofer who's writing this document of
sale, has to check with me for three things. Number one is
שיעבוד. shibud. Am I agreeing to encumber my property for this insurance
for Michael for the purchase, meaning that if it actually gets taken,
Michael does have a right to come and to get paid back
from me. It's like you automatically grant me title insurance. You automatically,
right, well, you don't. The סופר sofer has to ask. Does Dov
want to put in, you know, my... Right well you I don't
so for so for so the סופר sofer has to ask says
to דוב Dov do you want to put in you know Michael
of course wants to דוב Dov are you agreeing to put in
שעבוד shibud that he has that he has title insurance on this?
Or not title insurance let's not call it that because that's going
to be a different case title insurance is when you didn't really
own I didn't own right. We'll get to that in a minute.
Right. Anyway right. But it's not alone. Anyway, to protect Michael insurance
against some creditor coming and taking that land away from Michael. I
totally own it. There's no question I own the land. That's not
the problem. Problem is I owe money. And that land has liens
on it. So somebody might might execute those liens and then Michael
won't have the property. So this is also אחריות. achrayus. That is
אחריות, achrayus, right. Yeah, but the question is that אחריות achrayus cannot
be assumed. Okay. In a sale אחריות achrayus the why are we
using the word שעבוד? shibud? So I'll get to that in a
minute. It's a double point. Yeah well it's a double first of
all שעבוד shibud has a ש shin so that already fixes it
but it's a double point. It's important and I want to get
back to what חנה Chena said in a minute, which is there's
two things that I have to agree to. Number one is אחריות.
achrayus. I have to agree to basically protect give you know give
insurance to the fact that if that land is taken. And number
two, that insurance also creates liens on my property. So it's one
thing to give him insurance and he needs his ten thousand dollars
back and I have ten thousand dollars I have to pay it
to him. But let's say I don't have the ten thousand dollars
but I sold property since then. Can he now to get be
reimbursed for the property that was taken from him, now go seize
other property of mine that I've sold to be reimbursed for his
property? That's what a lien is. Okay so the שעבוד shibud here
contains both ideas actually. Both the sense that there is אחריות achrayus
that I am insuring it and that I am giving him liens
on my property. Now what are the other two? Okay, שבח shevach
and שפר. shefer. So שבח shevach is what? שבח shevach is let's
say Michael has put in another five thousand dollars into that property
to develop it and then it gets taken. Okay. Am I agreeing
to reimburse Michael not just for his ten thousand dollars that he
initially you know whatever that he initially paid for the plot of
land but the other five thousand dollars that since then he's it's
improved and he's invested am I also willing to reimburse him for
that. Now you might say that's crazy why is that my responsibility?
Well first of all it is my loan that got us to
see- and number two is if the guy seized his property for
a fifteen thousand dollar loan and that's why he seized it from
Michael, so I actually essentially right Michael paid five thousand dollars of
my loan for me, right. So I really do need to reimburse
Michael for his new five thousand dollar investment into that property. Okay
so that's the שבח. shevach. But you get the property you take
the property- no the property was taken אלי Eli there took the
property I owed אלי Eli fifteen thousand dollars. Michael paid me ten
thousand for the land. He invested five thousand. אלי Eli came and
took it for a fifteen thousand dollar loan that I had. So
that's the original loan. What? I borrowed fifteen thousand dollars from אלי
Eli years ago. Okay so now Michael wants his ten thousand dollars
back in cash and he'd like to be and he wants to
be reimbursed for his five thousand that he invested and I'm the
logical person that should give him that because his property has now
paid off a fifteen thousand dollar loan of mine not a ten
thousand dollar loan of mine. Even if it doesn't happen right? To
make sure that the property is worth ten thousand- yeah exactly. So
anyway so the סופר sofer also has to ask am I willing
to protect Michael for the שבח. shevach. Okay now what is the
שפר? shefer? שפר shefer is the question about the שפר נכסין shefar
nichsin which is that Michael has the right to collect from the
best of my property. Okay you might remember that from a בבא
קמא Bava Kamma right from a בבא קמא Bava Kamma concept. Okay
so להגבות מן העידית. l'hagvos min ha'idis. Okay anyway all those three
things have to be asked. Alright now let me look at just
check one רש"י Rashi about one thing one minute. All those things
have to be what? Have to be asked by the סופר. sofer.
Right so right so רש"י Rashi I just was double checking רש"י.
Rashi. רש"י Rashi makes the point that חנה Chena did that the
שעבוד shibud is not just the שעבוד shibud it's both אחריות achrayus
and the שעבוד. shibud. A the agreement to insure it and B
to have to create loans. Anyway so now the סופר sofer has
to check all those three things for me when I'm selling property
to Michael. Am I giving him those three things? What do you
see? You see if he didn't check we cannot assume that there's
a lien on the land. We don't assume אחריות טעות סופר. achrayus
ta'us sofer. Okay everybody with that? Right no you're not with that?
So when I'm selling Michael a plot of land the סופר sofer
has to ask דוב Dov do you want to give him insure
it and give him שעבודים. shibudim. Do you want to protect him
even against שבח. shevach. Do you want to even give him you
know the best of it. Okay so i get to make I
get to make a choice about all of those. And presumably if
he didn't ask and he didn't write those in we don't assume
that they're present. Those are all opt-in cases, right. So you see
that אחריות achrayus is an opt-in it's not an opt-out it's not
a טעות סופר. ta'us sofer. And it's not assumed. It has to
be asked, okay. So the גמרא Gemara said this a little bit
different though אחריות achrayus is on the שעבוד. shibud. Right so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Could be and also well no
he does say שעבוד shibud so it's both points, okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says
לימא מאן דאמר הא לא אמר הא leima mandamar ha lo amar
ha let's say the one who says one point about שמואל Shmuel
that אחריות achrayus No, the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, כאן בשטר הלואה. kan beshtar halva'ah. No, there's a big
difference between a loan document and a sale document. בשטר הלואה, beshtar
halva'ah, if Michael is borrowing money from me, דלא יהיב איניש זוזי
בכדי—I'm delo yahiv inish zuzei bechdi sorry, I'm borrowing money from Michael.
Michael is not going to throw away his money for nothing. He's
going to want to make sure that he can get, right, reimbursed.
You want a secured loan. You want there to be, to be,
to know that you can get reimbursed. So therefore, we're going to
assume that he's going to, of course, there will always be liens
present. What person would loan money and risk not recollecting it? So
that's by default that he's got liens, okay? That's the loan document.
כאן, kan, but when Michael's buying the plot of land from me,
מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, we're talking about a purchase, דעביד איניש דזבין
ארעא ליומי. de'avid inish dezavin ar'a leyomei. It's possible that you're buying
a plot of land just for a day. Not really, okay, but
the point is, is that the whole point of lending money is
to get it back. So your whole focus is on making sure
you're going to get it back. Here, you know, the point of
buying the land was to have the land to use. You're not
expecting, Michael hopes it never comes to it that he has to
come to me and ask to be reimbursed. Right? That's like a
worst case scenario. Best case is that, right, by a loan you're
always going to come back to me to get reimbursed, so you
want to know there's property there securing it. You want to know
there are liens. In this case, right, he's hoping that it'll never
come to it, that he'll have the property for forever. So of
course it's smart for him to protect his interests, but that's an
opt-in. Not only that, right, maybe I agreed to sell to Michael
at a lower price if he agrees to not ask for insurance.
Okay? So there it's not about getting the money back that of
course you're going to want to protect it and make sure it's,
in the loan it's all about getting the money back, so of
course you're going to be the lien to help you ensure you'll
get it back. Here it's about buying the piece of property, okay?
So therefore you might not protect that. You might be willing to
risk it, especially if I'm willing to even lower the price if
you're willing to risk it because all you really want is the
property. You don't want to have to come back to me to
get reimbursed. Yes? As of now, according to his other מימרא, memra,
you don't have an obligation to notify of the liens if they
didn't ask. So that's a good point. You know, the idea that
there are, that you know, that the liens are created by written
documents is exactly because the idea is that there's like a public
record. So it really is the person's responsibility to do, the buyer's
responsibility to do that record research. Of course, the problem with that
logic is, you know, today you go to, you know, you can
go to whatever office it is, right, and you can do a
title search and you can find out if there are liens and
they're registered in a central place. Right? The fact that what, maybe
online even. The fact that, you know, I have ten שטרות shtarot
against me and those שטרות shtarot create liens, right, there's no central
repository where you can find out what are the שטרות shtarot against
me. You're just supposed to know about it because a שטר shtar
is supposed to create a קול, kol, you know. Now it'd be
one thing if they said for to create a lien you have
to process a שטר shtar in בית דין beis din and בית
דין beis din has to keep a record of the שטרות, shtaros,
right, so it's not a perfect system in this way. But yes,
the assumption is is that you have, you're able to find out
about it and you have to do the research. You know? What's
the force of the word ליומי? leyomei? Even for just one day.
Like you can't say, well if I had it for a year
then but of course for, if the guy seized it a day
after the purchase, of course that would be a case where I
would expect to be able to be reimbursed. No, you know, if
you don't say it, you don't get it. This is fundamentally a
purchase. It is not about getting your money back. Okay, the purchase
is the purchase is permanent even if the owner then decides after
one day to do something else? No, even if the creditors come
in and seize it the day later. The guy who purchased it
can't come and say, oh of course in that case I expected
to get reimbursed because they came and they seized it. You don't
even have a thirty day warranty, okay? You're buying it and if
you don't protect yourself then we're assuming that, you know, you got
your product and you're, you know, it's about a sale. It's not
about getting your money back. So, okay, yes. There's no interest in
this situation. Correct. We're going to get to that later, but that's
correct, because otherwise it would be a ריבית ribbit issue, correct. Yeah,
I mean look, what if it increases in value? What? Does this
land ever? It might, sure. In that case they can make a
profit? No, they cannot. If I lend you a thousand dollars and
I have lien on your property and right now it's worth a
thousand dollars and you sell it or whatever and then it's time
to pay and you don't have the money and I take the
property, which is like predatory lending practices as of right either as
the way to get your property. Anyway, if that property is now
worth two thousand, I only get to seize half of it. I
don't get to seize the whole thing. I only get to seize
the amount of the property that's worth my loan at the time
when I'm being reimbursed. No, that's the sad part about this, is
that all of these poor מלוות malves that they have to go
to all this effort to get reimbursed and it's like the best
case scenario is that they don't lose money. They're not getting anything
for all their effort because you can't charge interest. Why would there
be a Torah financial system because you can't make money? I know.
Yeah, but the point is that all that is nice so that
we don't make more obstacles than already exist, but there's still no
incentive to lend money. The best case scenario is you went through
all this effort and you got your money back. That's the best
case scenario. Exactly. Now, by the way, look at תוספות. Tosfos. שיעבוד
צריך להימלך. shibud tzarich limalech. תוספות Tosfos says this is a point
that about it being two points here, about it being both אחריות
achrayus and שיעבוד. shibud. תוספות Tosfos and רש"י Rashi says this as
well, but תוספות Tosfos says it a little more explicitly. תוספות Tosfos
says בשטרי מקח, bishtarei mekach, we're talking here what we said about
a sale document, ואי לא כתב ליה, ve'ee lo kasav lei, and
if you did not write that you had a lien for reimbursing
the guy if the property got seized, מנכסי חרי נמי לא גבי.
minichsei chari nami lo gavi. Okay, you can't even collect from unencumbered
property. You cannot get reimbursed. Okay, ואי בעל חוב טרפא לה, ve'ee
baal chov tarpa la, etc., etc. Okay, then he's going to quote
a later גמרא. Gemara. So basically, okay, by a loan, of course
the debt is always there, and because the debt is always there
and it's always about being reimbursed, the liens are always there. By
a sale, it's about owning the property, and therefore you don't even
assume אחריות. achrayus. You don't even assume insurance. Even insurance has to
explicitly be opted in and with that opting in to get the
liens. Okay? So there's a major difference between a loan and a
sale. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, אמר אביי: Amar Abaye:
ראובן שמכר שדה לשמעון. Reuven shemachar sadei l'Shimon. ראובן Reuven sold the
field to שמעון. Shimon. ובא בעל חוב דראובן. Uva ba'al chov d'Reuven.
Okay, we'll call him לוי. Levi. Okay, well no, let's call him
somebody else, we'll call him לוט. Lot. Okay, so לוט Lot came,
ובא בעל חוב דראובן, uva ba'al chov d'Reuven, he's a bad guy,
he's seizing property. וקא טריף לה מיניה, Veka taraf lah minei, and
he is taking the property away from שמעון. Shimon. All right, so
got it? All right, ראובן Reuven sold to שמעון Shimon here, we'll
just do it with me. I sold to Charlie here, Eli, sorry
for calling you לוט Lot before, Eli. I sold to Charlie property,
Eli came and who I owe money to and took the property
away from Charlie. Okay, דינא הוא דאזיל ראובן ומשתעי דינא בהדיה. Dina
hu d'azil Reuven umishtaei dina bahadei. Now I, now Charlie is going
to... who's going to go in a court case with Eli to
try to protect the property? Certainly Charlie, because even though he might
be able to get reimbursed
from me or we'll see in a minute, you know, he doesn't
want to go to that trouble. He wants to keep the property.
There was a reason he bought that property. So he's going to
go to the court with Eli and say, no, I think Dov
paid you the loan, I think the document's a forgery, a million...
did I skip a little bit? Did I skip a little bit?
Yeah, where you are. I'm sorry. I'm front on the page though.
I skipped, I apologize. Yeah, I skipped the whole case that illustrated
this. All right, I'm sorry. It was all a good test. Okay,
I skipped the whole case that was just a nice illustration of
the rule we just said before. I'm sorry. כי הא דאבוה, Ki
ha d'Avuha, thank you, last word's דאבוה, d'Avuha, thank you very much.
כי הא דאבוה בר איהי, Ki ha d'Avuha bar Ihi, okay, this
person אבוה Avuha the son of איהי, Ihi, זבין עליתא מאחתיה. zavin
alisa me'achatei. He purchased a second story from his sister. אתא בעל
חוב טרפא מיניה. Ata ba'al chov tarfa minei. And then his sister's
creditor came and took his property away from him. אתא לקמיה דמר
שמואל. Ata lekamei d'Mar Shmuel. So he came to מר שמואל, Mar
Shmuel, he wanted to be reimbursed. The property he just purchased was
seized by a creditor. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so שמואל Shmuel said
to him, כתבה לך אחריות? Kasvah lach achrayus? Did she write for
you אחריות? achrayus? Did she insure that property for you in case
a creditor would come take it? אמר ליה, Amar lei, לא. lo.
No, she did not explicitly write the insurance in the document. And
again, this was a sale without insurance written in. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, אם כן זיל לשלמא. im kein zil l'shlama. If so, go
in peace, goodbye, okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, והא מר הוא דאמר
אחריות טעות סופר? ve'ha mar hu d'amar achrayus ta'us sofer? Wait one
minute, you're שמואל. Shmuel. There's a reason I went to you. You're
the guy who says that even if you don't write אחריות, achrayus,
it's assumed to be present. אמר ליה, Amar lei, הני מילי בשטרי
הלואה. hani mili bishtarei halva'ah. That's by a loan document. That's where
we assume it to be. אבל בשטרי מקח וממכר לא. Aval bishtarei
mekach umimkar lo. But not in a purchase sale document. דעביד איניש
דזבין ארעא ליומי. D'avid inish d'zavin ar'ah l'yomei. People will sell land
even for one day or purchase land even for one day. The
point was a purchase, the point was not getting your money back.
And therefore if you want to insure that you can get your
money back, that is a separate thing that has to be written
in. You see why I skipped, because it was the exact same
line that got repeated later. Even in families and even in family,
right? I know this is like on every page of the... don't
you think it's interesting that it's first framed conceptually and abstract, and
then they have an exact case? In case you didn't get it,
but we have to give you... but I bet you you're more
likely to remember the case than you are the... 100 percent. Right.
And then I was thinking if I only had the case, I'd
have to work hard to like abstract it. Exactly. Yep. אמר אביי.
Amar Abaye. Now, back to the case we're talking about. ראובן שמכר
שדה לשמעון. Reuven shemachar sadei l'Shimon. Okay, I went ahead and I
sold the field to Charlie. באחריות. beachrayus. Now, I insured it. ובא
בעל חוב דראובן וקא טריף לה מיניה. Uva ba'al chov d'Reuven veka
taraf lah minei. Now Eli, who I owe a lot of money
to, is going and now he's seizing Charlie's property. Okay, now the
question is, both me... He wants it because even though he'd get
reimbursed from me, he'd rather not have to get reimbursed from me;
he'd rather be able to keep the plot of land himself, right?
I'd like to get rid of Eli because I don't want to
have to go ahead and now reimburse Charlie, okay? So because Charlie
is the one that immediately is having his field seized, he's the
obvious person that goes to court with Eli. But the point is
since it's about my money I borrowed from him, I can also
go to court and defend the case and defend against Eli. So
that's the teaching. דינא הוא Dina hu the law is דאזיל ראובן
ומשתעי דינא בהדיה de'azeil Reuven umishta'ei dina bahadei that I'm allowed to
as well go and join in the court case because if you
don't have standing you can't join in in the court case, okay?
Now if you're a witness of course you can come and testify,
but if you're there to make claims and counterclaims and challenges and
so on, you have to have standing. So the point is well
I also have standing and I'm also allowed to go to the
court case. Why? ולא מצי אמר ליה Velo matzi amar lei and
Eli can't say to me לאו בעל דברים דידי את lav ba'al
devarim didi at hey Dov, you're not my litigant, I'm dealing with
Charlie, I'm taking Charlie's land, you get out of here. No, that's
not a claim. דאמר ליה De'amar lei that I say back to
Eli דמפקת מיניה demafkat minei any property you take away from Charlie
עלי דידי הדר alai didi hadar he's going to ask me to
reimburse him for it because I insured it. So of course I'm
a litigant, right? I'm the insurer. I'm sure that's true in general,
right? That if you that if you're suing somebody or whatever, I
mean I think often it's the insurance company is directly represented in
court because they're the one that's going to have to pay in
the end. Okay, but anyway here of course I can go ahead
and be part of this court case. I don't want to have
to reimburse Charlie for property you seize from him unjustly. איכא דאמרי
Ika d'amri some say אפילו שלא באחריות afilu shelo beachrayus even if
I didn't insure the property, I have a right to go and
to also litigate the case and protect Charlie's interests. Why? נמי דאמר
ליה Nami de'amar lei because I can say to my creditor there,
to Eli, לא ניחא לי דלהוי לשמעון תרעומת עלי lo nicha li
delehavé leShimon taromet alai even if Charlie cannot force me to reimburse
him because I did not insure it, he's going to have complaints
against me. He's going to say how could you have done this
to me Dov? You sold me this property that there was this
outstanding loan on and I didn't know about this loan, and at
the end of the day I'm out all this money because of
you. So even just to protect myself which is interesting, it's not
a financial interest but to protect myself against that sense that he
has a legitimate complaint against me, that's enough to give me standing
as a litigant. That's definitely a big חידוש chiddush in terms of
that. Now by the way תוספות Tosafot has a long discussion which
what benefit does it do to have me in the court? Okay,
because even like what am I going to say? I'm going to
say, oh the loan's a document, oh the loan's been paid off.
So Charlie can say that too. Charlie can say it maybe it's
a forgery, maybe it's been paid off. In a way he even
has a better way of saying it because he actually like you
know like he can always just put out any speculation there; he
says I didn't borrow the money, who knows what the story is,
right? So he might be able to make any claim I can
make. So תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out what would the relevance
be of me being personally in court. One interesting theory that תוספות
Tosafot throws out is let's say Eli has witnesses that are my
relatives. If I show up in court, maybe we have to get
rid of those witnesses because now they're relatives to one of the
litigants. But תוספות Tosafot says you know what, that would be true
even if I didn't show up in court. The fact that ultimately
what's being ruled impacts me, he can't have witnesses that are my
relatives even if whether I'm in court or not in court, whether
I'm participating as a litigant or not. So that would not be
a נפקא מינה. nafka mina. In the end, one נפקא מינה nafka
mina תוספות Tosafot comes on is let's say based on another case,
Eli owes me a שבועה. shvua. So if I show up in
court, I can make him take a שבועה shvua for this other
case, and then by the rule of גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua force
him to make other שבועות. shvuos. Okay, so that's a very unique
type of a right that I have that's not even directly relevant
to the case and why it would help to have me in
court. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out other scenarios why
it would matter to have that person in court. Okay, but anyway
that is Abaye's view. What? וליכא דאמר U'leika d'amar when you did,
why does Abaye have to say that I'm allowed in either case?
Why is it important to rule that I can be in court?
Just make all the claims even without me there, okay? I mean
the other point of course could be it's just say that I'm
just a smarter lawyer and a litigant than Charlie is and I
can think up more good claims to make and more good challenges
to make, right? Especially in a system in which you don't have
lawyers, you know you want your litigant to be the one that's
smart enough to be able to make all the possible claims. All
right, so that's that teaching. Now we continue. But now we are
going but what we have done clearly here is we have shifted
the center of gravity of our discussion from loans to selling plots
of land with insurance. And that's going to be the remainder of
the focus. So let's continue. ואמר אביי Ve'amar Abaye Abaye said ראובן
שמכר שדה לשמעון שלא באחריות. Reuven shemachar sade leShimon shelo beachrayus. Okay,
once again I sold this plot of land. Charlie there I did
not give him insurance. ויצא עליה עסיקין. V'yatza alehah asikin. Now, עסיקין
asikin came out again. So what's עסיקין? asikin? So עסיקין asikin means
that there are people that are challenging whether it was really my
land or not. Okay, people say, "Whoa, Dov, that's land, we know
it's been in your possession for the last 20 years, but we
have evidence that it actually belonged to our great-grandfather and your great-grandfather
just sat on it and it never really belonged to him." And
like this whole big court right, I mean that happens sometimes, you
know, there's these big pieces of property that are held up in
development for decades because, you know, because there's a whole challenge about
who owns them. Okay, so I sold Charlie this land and then
all of a sudden this big court case has broken out and
it's a big question whether anybody is ever going to get to
use this plot of land. Okay, can Charlie void the sale? That's
the question. Okay, עד שלא החזיק בה, Ad she'lo hichzik bah, before
he has actually done a חזקה, chazakah, יכול לחזור בו. yachol lachzor
bo. Charlie can say, "Okay, forget it, I'm backing out." משהחזיק בה,
Mishe'hichzik bah, once he's done a חזקה, chazakah, אינו יכול לחזור בו,
eino yachol lachzor bo, he can't back out. דאמר ליה, De'amar lei,
'cause I can say to Charlie, "Hey Charlie, once you took possession
of it, חיישא דקטרי סברת וקבלת," chaisa d'katri savas ve'kabbalas, which literally
means a bag filled with knots, you, you know, you assessed it
and you purchased it. You know, it's like what, there's got to
be a good idiom for that, but like more than buyer beware.
But anyway, you know, but a bag of goods, that's the idiom.
Is that it? A bill of goods? A bag of goods? What's
the phrase? A bag of goods? He sold, no, I think he
sold him a bill of goods. He sold him a bill of
goods. Yeah, it means like whatever, it's like it's basically like this,
like stuff with garbage. Okay, anyway, you know, you knew what you
were getting yourself into, or you should have known, it's your problem,
not my problem. Okay, next. אימתי הוי חזקה? Eimatai havei chazakah? I'm
going to go back in a second, I just need to read
the next line. When is it considered that Charlie has done this
act of חזקה? chazakah? מכי דייש אמצרי, Miki deish amtzarei, when he
walked around the border and the circumference. Now, תוספות Tosfos says, "I
don't understand a thing that's going on here," says תוספות. Tosfos. First
of all, we know what a חזקה chazakah is. Why all of
a sudden you're introducing what is a חזקה chazakah on land? And
a חזקה chazakah is not walking around the border. A חזקה chazakah
is actually doing something to improve the land, like fixing a fence,
locking it, or something of that nature. Since when is walking around
the border a חזקה? chazakah? Point number one. Number two, I need
the גמרא Gemara to tell me that after he's done a קנין,
kinyan, that he can't, you know, reverse? Of course, you do the
קנין, kinyan, the sale's over, like what's the חידוש chiddush here? Right?
So and חזקה chazakah is a קנין. kinyan. And if he paid
money, then that'll be the קנין. kinyan. Like what's the גמרא Gemara
telling me? "Oh, once you've done a קנין kinyan then the קנין
kinyan is done"? So he says, "No, actually, what the גמרא Gemara
is telling me is that even after the קנין, kinyan, there's an
opportunity to back out." That there was a presumed sense of like
a, you know, isn't there something now like when you buy a
house, like you can before, like you have a period that even
after technically you've bought it, I think it's before the, what do
you call it, the... What? Right, with the bank there's a period
of rescission. There's a period of rescission. Oh, is there? And and
I think also that if if it hasn't had the final, who's
that guy that comes? Not the assessor, but somebody that does the,
anyway... Until it's been recorded maybe? Whatever. Anyway, so that's basically what
תוספות Tosfos says here, that even though in all other areas of
מקח וממכר mekach umimkar once the sale is final, it's final, by
real estate because of these big types of things that could happen,
right? These big types, you know, big, you know, title search, not
title search, whatever, challenges etc., there was a presumed period that you
could back out, you know, until you have done this like walking
around. And that finalizes it and made a statement that you could
no longer back out. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
Yes, you paid your money, you did your חזקה, chazakah, you did
all the formal acts of קנין, kinyan, and nevertheless the חידוש chiddush
here is that there's this other period that you can be back
out until you've done this walking around if, not just presumably not
just because you changed your mind, but because some new event came
to light and therefore you have that right. Now, in a different
גמרא, Gemara, not here, because it came up in בבא קמא, Bava
Kamma, תוספות Tosfos says how long is that period? Like let's say
you wait three years before doing the walking around. Logically there has
to be also like a calendar time limit to this. Okay, but
that's what's going on here. Okay, so that's the חידוש chiddush of
this גמרא. Gemara. And if that's true, that's a huge חידוש, chiddush,
that even after you're קונה koneh it, you can't back out, you
know, you can back out until you've done this act of walking
around. Is this the same word as בר מצוה? bar mitzvah? רש"י
Rashi does not read it that way. Is it the same word
as בר מצוה? bar mitzvah? Right, מצרא mitzra exactly means the boundary.
ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika de'amri, some say, אפילו באחריות נמי. afilu b'achrayut nami.
Now, can you back out even if it was sold with אחריות?
achrayut? Why? דאמר ליה, De'amar lei, because meaning basically what, you know,
here who who did I say in this scenario? Charlie bought the
land from me. So Charlie bought the land, so Charlie will say,
"Look, I know that I did the whole walk around or whatever
and I'm not allowed to back out, but, you know what? I'm
going to back out anyway." Why does he want to back out?
I mean, no, until now we said that was שלא באחריות. she'lo
b'achrayut. Why do we think אחריות achrayut was different? Because we thought
if I've insured the land... He's going to be able to get
the money back from me, right, if the land does eventually get
taken from him. So then why can't he just say look, let's
just be מבטל המקח m'vatel hamkach right now? Just give me the
money back. It's insured anyway, so you might have to eventually reimburse
me anyway. Why wait till we're in court and... right, so now
we're going to have to wait 20 years for this whole thing
to get resolved. I'm not going to be able to build on
it because it's all being challenged, and maybe 20 years from now
maybe I will have it, maybe I won't, but if I don't
I'm going to be able to get reimbursed from you. Just give
me back the money now. Okay, so that's what he says. So
that's why we thought אחריות achrayut maybe he could always back out.
But now we're saying even with אחריות, achrayut, after he's done the
walkaround, he can't. Why not? אפילו באחריות afilu b'achrayut he can't back
out after the walkaround. דאמר ליה, d'amar lei, because I can say
to Charlie, אחוי טרפך ואשלם לך, achvei tarpech v'ashalem lach, go show
me the documents that say that the land has been seized from
you and then I'll reimburse you. Okay, which basically means, sure it's
insured and I'm happy to pay the insurance once the land is
taken from you. Right now, it's your land that's under challenge, that's
being challenged. I'm sorry you can't do anything with it. Okay, but
I do not yet have to pay up the insurance. Okay, so
that is again, like it's an interesting variation. The reason we're bringing
it in here is because to what degree does insuring it make
a... might make a difference whether at what stage he's allowed to
back out. But the bigger חידוש chiddush is that even after purchasing
it, he has this period if something happens that he can still
take it back. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
איתמר. itmar. המוכר שדה לחבירו ונמצאת שאינה שלו. hamocher sadeh l'chaveiro v'nimtzet
she'einah shelo. Now this is not a case where it is, what
do you call it, where it's a, where some creditor comes and
seizes, seizes it. I sell it and it turns out it wasn't
mine. It could be that I knew, like, you know, I was
selling somebody the Brooklyn Bridge, I knew it wasn't mine or whatever,
I duped somebody, or it could just be an, you know, I
was, I, like, you know, it was an honest mistake. Like, I
inherited this from my father, I bought it from somebody else, you
know, three, three stages removed, it turns out that it had been
stolen land. Okay. But for whatever the reason is, I sold it
to Charlie and it's turned out that it was never my land
to begin with, and now it's taken from him and he wants
to reimburse, be reimbursed from me. Now תוספות Tosafot says, important, important
point: In this case, I do not need to write אחריות. achrayut.
Charlie is always entitled to get his money back. Even though when
my creditor takes it, he can't get his money back if I
haven't given him insurance, here he can. Why do you think there's
a difference? Exactly. If it turned out it wasn't my land, the
whole thing was a מקח טעות. mekach taut. If it was my
land and a creditor took it, it was a legitimate sale because
of the laws of liens and whatever, somebody was able to take
his property away from him, but it was, that was a legitimate
sale and without insurance he can't ask me to reimburse him. But
in the case that it wasn't mine, it was never a legitimate
sale. So of course he's entitled to his money back. Okay. And
תוספות Tosafot says, interestingly, not only is he entitled to his money
back, there are soon to be, to be liens on
my property if I
do a
מקח טעות. mekach taut. Why is that? Well תוספות Tosafot says that
if I go ahead and I sell Charlie this property which isn't
mine for $10,000, then it turns out
this was not a legitimate bill of sale, but you know
what it was? It
was a document that recorded the fact that Charlie gave me $10,000
and I gave him nothing. I gave him land that wasn't mine.
So essentially
it turns
out to
be a loan document. So
it's a little bit of a
חאפ, chap, like, but anyway. But that's the assumption the גמרא Gemara
has, that if you sell land that isn't yours, then you have
to reimburse even without insurance. It's not
about
insurance,
it was a false sale, and
your property, you're, there are liens on your property that the person
who purchased it can go ahead and get his money back even
from the purchasers. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
איתמר. itmar. המוכר שדה לחבירו ונמצאת שאינה שלו. hamocher sadeh l'chaveiro v'nimtzet
she'einah shelo. So somebody
sold a field to his friend, and it turned out that it
wasn't mine. רב אמר יש לו מעות ויש לו שבח. Rav amar
yesh lo ma'ot v'yesh lo shevach. If Charlie is coming to get
reimbursed, he can get his money back, and not only can he
get his money back, he can also get back any improvements that
he made on the property. Now that's a little funny because why
is he entitled to get back improvements he made on the property?
Like, that's not money I took from him. On the other hand,
like, you know, I sold some property that wasn't mine, maybe it's
just like a type of a liability I caused him to lose
that and so on. Okay, but that's what רב Rav says, he
can get back even improvements he made on the property. ושמואל אמר
מעות יש לו שבח אין לו. u'Shmuel amar ma'ot yesh lo shevach
ein lo. No, he can only get back the purchase price, he
can't get back improvements. Now, בעי מיניה רב הונא. ba'ei minei Rav
Huna. So they asked רב הונא. Rav Huna. פירש לו את השבח
מהו? perash lo et hashevach mahu? According to שמואל, Shmuel, if we
explicitly wrote in the document that I sold Charlie, "I am selling
you this land, and if it turns out that it is not
my property, I will reimburse you for the purchase price and for
any improvements." I wrote that explicitly in the document. Is he still
entitled to improvements, is he entitled to improvements according to שמואל? Shmuel?
מהו? mahu? טעמא דשמואל משום דלא פריש. ta'ama d'Shmuel mishum d'lo parish.
The reason that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says you don't get, he doesn't
get his שבח shevach, *shvach* because it was never said explicitly, so
we can't, you know, so all we have without making an explicit
insurance is only reimbursing him for the sale price. והכא פירש ליה
*v'hacha peirsh lei*, but here he says it explicitly, it's essentially a
type of an insurance, so therefore he should be entitled to it.
או דלמא *Od dilma*, or do we say no, טעמא דשמואל *tama
d'Shmuel* כיון דלית ליה קרקע *keivan d'leis lei karka*, at the end
of the day it wasn't my land. So what happened at the
end of the day? I just told you a minute ago, it's
a מקח טעות *mekach taus* or in a certain way it's a
loan. He gave me money that then I have to give it
back. So he gave me a
thousand dollars and I'm giving
back fifteen hundred, a
thousand plus his שבח shevach, *shvach*.
So it looks like
it's a case of interest. מחזי כריבית *Mechzi k'ribis*. Now it's not
ריבית ribis. *ribis*, it looks like ריבית *ribis*, because Charlie in the
end, he's not just asking for five hundred dollars extra, he spent
five hundred dollars improving the land that then got taken from him.
But nevertheless that's what it looks like. I didn't sell him land,
he gave me a thousand dollars and I'm giving him back fifteen
hundred. So maybe even if you make it explicit we can't do
it. Why can't we think of it as
a קנס *knas*? Well, we could, but that would be maybe according
to רב Rav *Rav* who says that basically יש לו שבח shevach.
*yesh lo shvach*, so then maybe you could sort of see it
like בית דין *beis din* imposing the קנס *knas*. But according to
שמואל Shmuel? *Shmuel* who says basically אין לו שבח shevach *ein lo
shvach* and it's only if I write it in, it's
certainly not a קנס *knas*, right? Should I
understand this to be now
a halachic category מחזי כריבית *mechzi k'ribis*? מחזי כריבית *Mechzi k'ribis*, oh
I'm telling
you, we have a פרק *perek*
coming up, איזהו נשך *eizehu neshech*. מחזי כריבית *Mechzi k'ribis* is at
least half of the concerns of ריבית *ribis*, yeah. One also wonders
if this would be a way, like one of those ways you
could trick do ריבית *ribis*. Hey, I'll tell you what Jenna, I'll
sell you the Brooklyn Bridge for ten thousand dollars. Exactly. But then
of course that really wouldn't work because then the person would have
to actually probably demonstrate the שבח shevach. *shvach* that it was increased
in order to get the additional money. But anyway. Alright. But let's
yeah, what's the פירוש *peirush*, how does that work? You, we, explicit
means like you write it in the document. שבח shevach, *Shvach*, yeah,
it's like insurance. You know, if I say explicitly in the document,
if it gets taken I will reimburse you for any שבח shevach.
*shvach*. Can you imagine, this is not like those as is sales
with the big D. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so okay, so אמר ליה
*amar lei*, you're accepting his honesty about that when he's being deceptive
about selling the land that doesn't even belong to him. No, the
person, no, whose honesty? No, the person is saying he'll cover the
improvement. He's saying he'll cover the improvement, I'm accepting that as a
legal commitment. I mean he writes it in the document. Okay, but
he could be the person who's selling this thing he doesn't even
own, right? Yes, because maybe he legally bound himself. And again I
want to point out that if it's נמצא שאינה שלו *nimtza she'eina
shelo*, doesn't mean that he's
a גזלן gazlan, *gazlan*. It could be that he genuinely thought this
was his property. I bought it from you, you bought it
from him, he bought it from five, twenty people back it was
stolen improperly, right? Which undermines the קנס *knas* idea, right? That's also
true, exactly. Yeah, it doesn't seem like we're dealing
with a קנס *knas* at all. We're talking about like legal liability.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: so
would it make a difference if he said it explicitly? אמר ליה
*amar lei*, he said back, אין ולא ורפיא בידיה *in v'la v'rafia
b'yadei*. Yes and no, and it was weak in his hands. Okay,
which means like, you know, he vacillated. He didn't know what the
answer was. He didn't know what the reason of שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*
was. אתמר *Itmar*, אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman אמר שמואל Shmuel. *amar
Rav Nachman amar Shmuel*: so now even though he didn't know, we
have a teaching that's going to make this clear. Said רב נחמן
Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* in the name of שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, מעות
יש לו שבח אין shevach in, לו *ma'os yesh lo shvach ein
lo*, that in this case where the field wasn't his, he has
to reimburse for the purchase price, the purchaser gets the money back
but he doesn't get the שבח shevach? *shvach* back. אף על פי
שפירש לו את השבח *Af al pi shepeirush lo es hashvach*, and
here this teaching answered our previous question. At least according to רב
נחמן *Rav Nachman*'s tradition, even if he explicitly promised to reimburse for
the שבח shevach, *shvach*, he does not get reimbursed for the שבח
shevach *shvach*. מאי טעמא *Mai tama*? כיון דקרקע אין לו *Keivan d'karka
ein lo*, since in the end the land never belonged to the
guy, שכר מעותיו הוא עומד ונוטל *sechar ma'osav hu omeid v'notel*, it
looks like this, actually the language here is even more than it
looks like. This language is, he is getting fee for his money.
Okay, it sounds like it's basically ריבית *ribis*. You know, you lent
a certain amount of money and you're getting back more. Of course
again, the reason you're getting back more is the land is worth
more. But again, it doesn't work even if you say it explicitly,
it looks like ריבית *ribis*. Fees for his money. Right. So I
want to actually say I was glossing over a little
bit. That there actually is a
difference between שבח shevach, *shvach* and יציאה *yetzia*. יציאה *Yetzia* is your,
you know, your costs, what you put in. שבח shevach *Shvach* is
the amount it improved. So it could be, now as opposed to
when you make home improvements, I know because I'm in the middle
of making some home improvements, that the שבח shevach *shvach* is always
less than the יציאה *yetzia*. Hopefully when you're developing real estate, the
שבח shevach. *shvach* is going to be more than the יציאה *yetzia*,
unless you're, well, okay, I wasn't going to say it. You can
figure out what I almost didn't say. Anyway, if you're developing real
estate if you know what you're doing, hopefully and you're whatever, the
שבח shevach *shvach* is going to be more than the יציאה *yetzia*.
So actually in that case Charlie really only put in two hundred
dollars but it improved five hundred and he actually wants to get
back, you know, but he lost now a property worth fifteen hundred.
Okay, so he wants to... be fully reimbursed, so he's not just
getting reimbursed for his investment, he's actually getting reimbursed for the full
new value of the improved value of the property. I was sort
of simplifying it before. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this.
איתיביה Eisivei רב לרב נחמן. le-Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן now quoting
שמואל Shmuel saying that you can get reimbursed for פירות peiros if
you say it explicitly. So he challenged רב נחמן for שבח, shevach.
excuse me. Yes. אין מוציאין
Ein
motzin
in a case that it was not yours. אין מוציאין לאכילת פירות
ולשבח קרקעות ולמזון אשה ובנות מנכסים משועבדים מפני תיקון העולם. Ein motzin
l'achilas peiros u'leshevach karka'os u'le-mezon isha u-banos mi-nechasim meshubadim mipnei tikkun ha-olam.
So here, let me start with your easy case, which is מזון
אשה ובנות. mezon isha u-banos. Okay, this is basically a guy gets
married, and
the
standard obligation in a כתובה kesubah is that if he dies, his
widow gets to be supported by the estate until she remarries, and
his daughters get to be supported by the estate because daughters don't
inherit, okay, but they get to be supported by the estate until
they marry. Now, let's say, okay, this guy's wife, widow, and daughters
are, the estate doesn't have any money in the bank, and but
they're entitled to get, to get their מזונות, mezonos, they're entitled to
get food and support until they, until, until if and when they
get married. So although there's no money in the bank for the
estate,
there actually is a lot of property
that the estate has sold, or that the husband sold before he
died. Now, this let's say has, they essentially have
if it's- it's
like a loan. Money is owed to them, it's
a debt that they
have a lien that they have against the estate. How much money
is owed to them? As- however much money it's going to take
to pay for their support. That's the money owed to them. Can
they go to people who have purchased property from the father before
he died and take the property out to pay for their מזונות?
mezonos? And the answer is no. Why is the answer no? מפני
תיקון העולם, Mipnei tikkun ha-olam, because a purchaser has no idea how
much is the outstanding debt on this
estate, right? If there's a
million dollars of debt, I know
when I purchase property, there's a
million dollars of debt. But if the אשה isha and the בנות
banos have this lien, the amount of money that that lien is
equal to is not determinate. Maybe the daughters will live till 80
and never get married. I don't know how much that amount of
debt is. So therefore, an indeterminate amount, we cannot allow there to
be a lien for an indeterminate amount. So that's the purpose of
מפני תיקון
העולם. mipnei tikkun ha-olam.
Did you have a question? Just not even if the guy hasn't
died yet, so then you're like also estimating based on is he
going to die and if so, when and how long is she
going to live? Right, well, that's true too, yeah. But he goes
on, why did you say even before he died? I always thought
the whole case was after he died. No, no, you can't- you
can't execute the lien until after he died, but it would be
regardless of whether he sold property... I just didn't want to limit
it to the property being sold after he died. The property could
be sold when he was alive, it doesn't matter. Right. What's the
relationship in the dollar amount so to speak between the amount specified
to the woman, yeah, in case of a divorce, and the 200
זוז? zuz? You don't know. It depends on how many years you're
talking about, depends on the style of living that they're used to.
I'm serious, that's why it's not exactly determinate. Of course, the thing
is you go to an actuary and I'm sure you could get
a good equivalent based on averages. Exactly. But anyway, ביז דא עז
נישט משנה, Biz da es nisht meshaneh, that's the rule that you
do not have liens. Liens do not exist for amounts that are
indeterminate. That's מזון אשה ובנות, mezon isha u-banos, מפני תיקון העולם. mipnei
tikkun ha-olam. Now there are two other cases, which is what we're
going to look at. So let's look at that again. אין מוציאין
לאכילת
פירות Ein motzin l'achilas peiros for eating a fruit, ולשבח קרקעות u'leshevach
karka'os for the improvement of land, ולמזון אשה ובנות מנכסים משועבדים מפני
תיקון העולם. u-le-mezon isha u-banos mi-nechasim meshubadim mipnei tikkun ha-olam. So we're
going to be focusing on the שבח קרקע shevach karka because we
think that's our case, okay. It says now, ממישעבדי הוא דלא מפקינן,
Mi-meshubadi hu d'lo mafkinan, we don't use it from the purchasers, from
the encumbered property, הא מבני חרי, ha m'benei chorin, but from unencumbered
property, from the- from the person himself, מפקינן, mafkinan, right, because the
wife and the daughter, for example,
can obviously get supported directly from the funds of the estate. Okay,
וקתני מיהא V'kasani miha לשבח קרקעות. l'shevach karka'os. So one of the
cases is improvement of land. And improvement of land
you can't get from the liens because again, you don't know how
much the land is going to be improved if somebody's coming to
get reimbursed for- meant- being reimbursed for improvement of land. That's an
indeterminate amount. But you can
get
reimbursed from the person himself. So what is the case that somebody
is coming to someone and is asking to be reimbursed for the
improvement of the land? Presumably, it's our case. מאי לאו, Mai lav,
are we not talking about a case בלקוח מגזלן? be-loke'ach mi-gazlan? That
somebody purchased
stuff- now
it's calling
him a גזלן, gazlan, not just נמצאת שאינה שלו- nimtzes she-eina shelo
purchased something
from somebody, turned out that it was not that guy's land to
begin with. So he purchases
from me, he made all this שבח, shevach, he now is- it
turned out it wasn't my land, he wants to be reimbursed for
the שבח. shevach So he can't go to לקוחות lakuchos because the
amount is indeterminate how much that שבח shevach, will be, but he
can come to me, okay, so if you can basically- The point
is it says you can be reimbursed for שבח. shevach, That's the
point. You don't have lien for שבח, shevach but you can be
reimbursed for שבח. shevach So isn't that our scenario? Don't you see
that in the case of a גזלן, the person who made the
improvements can be reimbursed for his שבח? shevach Okay, doesn't this prove
against שמואל? Shmuel So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי לאו מלוקח מגזלן?
Mai lav milokeach migazlan? לא דבעל חוב. Lo debaal hov. No, that's
not
it. The case was I sold to Charlie the land and it
was mine, but some creditor came and seized it. And now Charlie
wants to be reimbursed, not just for the loss of the purchase
price, but for the current value of the land. Okay. So the
גמרא, Gemara that's what we're talking about, that he can get reimbursed
from me, but
not from other people who bought my land. One minute. אי דבעל
חוב, I debaal hov, if that's the case, אימא רישא. eima reisha.
How about the first case in the משנה? Mishnah? אין מוציאין לאכילת
פירות. Ein motzi'in la'achilat peirot. Now you cannot... now what's the case
of אכילת פירות? achilat peirot? אכילת פירות achilat peirot means not that
Charlie went ahead and improved the land and it's שבח, shevach but
actually that there was I sold him an orchard and it had
all these fruit that were like ready to be eaten. So that's
not considered שבח of the land, cause that's temporary. You're going to
harvest the fruit. It's not really like a lasting improvement of the
land, okay? But now the land got seized from him, and he
wants to be reimbursed for his loss of fruit. Okay. That would
be the case of similar to be reimbursed for שבח, he wants
to be reimbursed for his loss of fruit. So the גמרא's going
to say that scenario doesn't work
if it was a creditor who seized the land. It works if
it was not my land and the original owner seized it. He
would get back the land with the fruit. But
if it was a creditor, the creditor only has liens on land,
and fruit that's ready to be harvested is not considered to be
connected to the land anymore. So it's not considered to be... the
creditor doesn't have rights to those fruit. So if we're dealing with
a case of a creditor and that's why he can come and
get שבח from me, then it would not... we would not be
able to be talking about him getting fruit cause the creditor wouldn't
be able to take the fruit. Okay.
So let's take a look. אין מוציאין לאכילת פירות. Ein motzi'in la'achilat
peirot. אי דבעל חוב, I debaal hov, בעל חוב מי ספי פירא?
baal hov mi safei peirei? A בעל חוב baal hov would never
have taken the fruit that Charlie would now be able to ask,
be wanting to get reimbursed. ואמר שמואל, Ve'amar Shmuel, the same שמואל
Shmuel said: בעל חוב גובה את השבח, Baal hov govech et hashevach,
when the creditor comes and he takes the land from Charlie, he
can get the land with the improved value. שבח אין, only the
improved value, אבל פירות לא, aval peiros lo, but not the פירות.
peiros. אלא פשיטא, Ela peshita, דגזל ונגזל. degozal veinigzal. If Charlie is
coming to get reimbursed for the fruit, it's not because the creditor
took it, it's because the original owner took it, that it wasn't
my land. ומדרישא Umidei reisha דגזל ונגזל, degozal veinigzal, and if that
case where the case where the where the person whose original it
was stolen and the person whose original land took it back, סיפא
נמי, seifa nami, the case of שבח where Charlie wants to get
reimbursed is נמי דגזל ונגזל. nami degozal veinigzal. Is that case. So
basically the case of fruit is a case where it was stolen,
and the presumably therefore the case
of improvements is a case where it was stolen. And in both
of those cases it says that I have to reimburse Charlie. He
doesn't have lien, he can't get it from other people, but I
have to reimburse him. So you see it's a proof against שמואל.
Shmuel If it's stolen, he has to be reimbursed. He gets reimbursed
even for the שבח. So the גמרא says: No, מידי איריא? midi
irya? הא כדיתא והא כדיתא. Ha kide'isa veha kide'isa. So no, they're
different cases. The case of פירות peiros cannot be a case
of a creditor, has to be a
case of original owner. So the original... in that case it
was
stolen. The original owner came,
took it away from Charlie, Charlie wants to get
his fruit back from me, I have to reimburse him. But the
case of שבח was
not a case when it was stolen, that was a case
of a creditor and that's why he wants to now get reimbursed
from me. So I think we did that a
little fast and I know we're already at 8:30. Let me just
sort of show where we're ending up. Okay. So there the case
here... okay that's ראובן Reuven I guess, we'll do
שמעון. Shimon. Okay. So I sold a plot of land,
okay, and then where's the
hundred? And now it's
worth a
hundred fifty, that's שבח. And now it's also got some fruit, okay.
And those are the פירות. peiros. Okay. Now this is going to
be taken from him by... okay, here it gets taken, it gets
seized. Okay. The whole thing, the פירות peiros and the שבח, okay,
and he wants now to get reimbursed... ah! He wants now to
get reimbursed. Okay. והלכה היא, Vahalacha hi, he can get reimbursed
from the seller, but
אין מוציאין
לאכילת פירות ולשבח
ein motzi'in
la'achilat peiros
uleshevach from
if the purchaser sold his property and anyone else he can't go
to those other people because it's indeterminate how much the שבח and
the פירות peiros will be, but he can always go back to
the original guy. That's the basic point, okay? So the point is,
ah, what's the case that it was seized? Presumably the case it
was seized was it was proven not to be ראובן's Reuven land.
So you see he can go back and get reimbursed against שמואל
Shmuel. even for the שבח, like even when it was not ראובן's
Reuven land, he can get reimbursed because it's... telling you he can
get reimbursed. So it says no, this case of it being seized
is a case where it was creditors who seized it and not
the original owner.
The only problem is that the case of פירות peirot wouldn't be
seized by creditors. Creditors could seize the שבח, they couldn't seize the
פירות. peirot. Okay? So what we're saying is fine, but at least
this case, this case of the שבח is seized by creditors and
this case of the פירות peirot is going to be seized by
the original owner, original owner. Okay? Because the original owner should have
got The original owner right is entitled to the פירות. peiros. So
from what so from this case that it was seized and that
he's entitled to be
reimbursed is not a proof against שמואל Shmuel. because this is
not a case of נגזל,
nigzal,
this is
a case of a
creditor and therefore in that case he is entitled to be reimbursed
for he is entitled to be reimbursed. This case which is about
פירות peirot we're going to have to go back to because this
case still
seems
to be a contradiction to שמואל
because whether you're talking about שבח or פירות, peirot, the original owner
seized it and now he's going to go and he's going to
get reimbursed for it. So whether he's going to get reimbursed for
the שבח or get reimbursed for the פירות, peirot, it seems to
be a proof against שמואל because שמואל's idea was if it turns
out it wasn't your property, you can never get back the guy
can never get back more money than he paid. It looks like
ריבית. So whether he's getting back for the שבח or the פירות,
peiros, right once we've
conceded that
this case is a case of that it was never his property
and the original owner took it and now he's going to go
and get back his original money plus the פירות, peiros,
that should be a proof against
שמואל.
So this wasn't a proof against שמואל. This might
be a
creditor and
by a creditor you are entitled to get
back more because it
was a legitimate sale. But when it was a נגזל nigzal and
it
wasn't a legitimate sale you should never be entitled to get back
more and so we're going to have to go in the end
this is we're going to have to deal with this case. Okay?
So we're not done.
The evidence is sort of stacking up to show that he can
get back more than you know even in a case of נגזל
nigzal more than he originally paid and we'll continue with that tomorrow.
So wait, if it's the owner